Guide to the Bourne Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bourne Family Papers
1793-1919
Gen MSS 1438
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(6 boxes)
The Bourne Family Papers consists of materials that document the lives of abolitionist, minister and newspaper editor George Bourne, his wife Mary Oland Stibbs Bourne and their descendants. The majority of materials in the collection document the professional careers of George Bourne and his son Theodore Bourne. George Bourne's papers include an Anti-Slavery Lecture of 1837 along with other religious writings. Theodore Bourne's papers chiefly relate to African American repatriation organizations such as the African Christian Civilization Society. Correspondence between the Bourne and Stibbs family in England and the United States document George and Mary Bourne's new life as they settled throughout the United States. Poems written by members of the Bourne Family and others such as abolitionists James Montgomery, Helen Maria Williams and John Greenleaf Whitter are also included.
Bourne family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. (Swann Galleries sale, 2014 March 27, lot 41) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
George Bourne was born on June 13, 1780 in Westbury, Wiltshire, England. In 1804, he married Mary Oland Stibbs (1780-1851), and they moved from England to the United States where they had ten children. George Bourne and his family moved frequently, settling in New York, Maryland, Virginia, and Pennsylvania. In 1810, George Bourne moved his family to New Glasgow, Virginia and became a Presbyterian minister. It was in Virginia that Bourne witnessed the American slavery system and as a result, became one of the founders of the American Anti-Slavery Society. Bourne wrote many anti-slavery articles as the editor for the Christian Intelligencer and the Baltimore Daily Gazette. George Bourne wrote The Book and Slavery Irreconcilable (1816) and delivered The Anti-Slavery Lecture of 1837 in Newburyport, Massachusetts. George Bourne died in New York on November 20, 1845. George Bourne's sons Theodore Bourne (1822-1910), William Oland Bourne (1819-1901) and Rowland Hill Bourne (1812-1886) held similar anti-slavery and religious interests. William Oland Bourne and Rowland Hill Bourne became ministers while Theodore Bourne participated in African American repatriation movements such as the African Christian Civilization Society, which sought to encourage African American immigration to West Africa including Liberia and present day Nigeria.
Scope and Contents
The Bourne Family Papers consist of materials that document the lives of abolitionist, minister and newspaper editor George Bourne, his wife Mary Oland Stibbs Bourne and their descendants. The majority of materials in the collection document the professional careers of George Bourne and his son Theodore Bourne. George Bourne's papers include an Anti-Slavery Lecture of 1837 as well as other religious writings. Theodore Bourne's papers relate to African American repatriation organizations such as the African Christian Civilization Society founded by Henry Highland Garnet. Correspondence between the Bourne and Stibbs family in England and the United States documents George and Mary Bourne's new life as they settled throughout the United States. Poems written by members of the Bourne Family such as Theodore Bourne and his brother William Oland Bourne are found in the collection. Other writings from abolitionists James Montgomery, Helen Maria Williams and John Greeenleaf Whitter are also included.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence (1793-1919). II. Professional Papers (1793-1910). III. Personal Papers (1793-1910).
Abolitionists -- United States; African Americans -- Colonization -- Africa; African Americans -- Social conditions -- 19th century; Clergy -- United States; Presbyterian Church -- Clergy; Poets -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Poets -- United States -- 19th century; Bourne family; Bourne, George, 1780-1845; Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1780-1851; Bourne, Rowland Hill, 1812-1886; Bourne, Theodore, 1822-1910; Bourne, Wm. Oland (William Oland), 1819-1901; Montgomery, James, 1771-1854; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892; Williams, Helen Maria, 1762-1827
- Correspondence, 1793–1919; Series I
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries: Family Correspondence and General Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Family Correspondence includes letters exchanged between the Bourne and Stibbs family in England as well as in the United States. Mary Oland Stibbs Bourne corresponded frequently with her family in England about family life in the United States. She also corresponded with her children as they grew into adults.
  General Correspondence includes letters from friends and colleagues of the Bourne Family. George Bourne wrote frequently to other ministers and abolitionists such as Dan Bryan regarding anti-slavery movements. Correspondence to Theodore Bourne chiefly comes from members of the African Christian Civilization Society and the African Aid Society. Abolitionist and physician Martin R. Delany, teacher Robert Campbell and Lord Alfred Churchill of England corresponded with Theodore Bourne with regard to African American repatriation.
  - Family Correspondence
    - Letters received by George Bourne
      - Christmas, Joseph Stibbs, 1822–1824 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Stibbs, Christopher, 1807–1825 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Stibbs, Joseph, 1810–1812 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 47)
      - Unidentified, Circa 1793-1845 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Unidentified, Circa 1793-1845 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 48)
    - Letters received by Mary Oland Stibbs Bourne
      - Bourne, George, 1799–1819 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 49)
      - Bourne, Rowland Hill, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Stibbs, Christopher, 1839–1847 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Stibbs, George Pimes, 1797 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 50)
      - Stibbs, Thomas, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters received by Theodore Bourne
      - Bourne, Charles, 1870–1871 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Bourne, Emma, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Bourne, Freddie, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Bourne, George, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Bourne, Leila, 1870–1871 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1842 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 51)
      - Bourne, Rowland Hill, 1844–1857 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Field, Addie, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Unidentified, 1900–1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters received by Samuel Bourne
      - Bourne, George, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters received by Mary Bourne Nesbit
      - Bourne, Rowland Hill, 1854–1862 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters received by Christopher Stibbs
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1793 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 52)
    - Letters received by Mary Stibbs
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1805 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 53)
      - Parsons, Thomas, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letters received by Sarah Stibbs
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1805–1818 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters received by Thomas Oland Stibbs
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1804–1805 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Bourne, Mary Oland Stibbs, 1804 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 54)
    - Letters received by Pierson, A.R.
      - Parsons, Frank, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified correspondence, 1810–1889 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General Correspondence
    - Letters received by George Bourne
      - Bryan, Dan, 1811–1817 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Phillips, Wendell, Circa 1800-1845 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Strong, Thomas, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Unidentified, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Letters received by Theodore Bourne
      - Bean, Sarah, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Bourget Ignac, Bishop of Montreal, 1843–1848 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Campbell, Robert, 1858–1859 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Chamerovzov, L.A., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Churchill, Alfred Spencer, Lord, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Clegg, Thomas, 1853–1860 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Coates, Benjamin, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Crosby, Howard, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Delany, Martin R., 1876 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Harrison, Barry, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Hodgekins, Thomas, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Knopp, Major, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Monteith and Hall, 1889–1890 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Mountain, A.W., 1846 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Pentalarge, Thomas, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Sury, W.D., 1855 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Williams, A.S., 1894 (Box 1, Folder 44)
        Two photographs are included with this letter. One photograph is of Thomas Roberts and his brother of Monrovia, Liberia (1886) and another of school children (undated).
      - Invitations, Circa 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Unidentified, 1842–1861 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Professional Papers, 1793–1910; Series II
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Professional Papers documents the careers of the Bourne family. Religious texts written by George Bourne for the Christian Intelligencer, as well as anti-slavery texts such as The Anti-Slavery Lecture of 1837, are in this series. Theodore Bourne's writings include "A Biographical Sketch of George Bourne" along with an account of George Bourne and his interaction with Thomas Paine. Theodore Bourne's papers from his work as secretary of the African Christian Civilization Society is well documented. Publications written by members of the African Christian Civilization Society such as Quaker Benjamin Coates and Jehu T. Dimey are also included. Maps illustrating nineteenth-century African nations are found within the series. Other papers from organizations such as the African Aid Society, Freedmen's Mission Aid Society, International Migration Society and the American Missionary Association are also included in the series. Material related to members of the Bourne family including William Oland Bourne can also be found. Writings by others include clippings by John Greenleaf Whittier, original poems by James Montgomery and Samuel W. Seton as well as writings by Helen Maria Williams.
  - African Aid Society, 1860–1861 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - African Aid Society, 1861 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 55)
  - African Christian Civilzation Society, 1858–1897 (Box 3, Folder 59-62)
  - African Christian Civilization Society, 1860 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 56)
  - African Native Agency Committee, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - African Steamship Company, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - The American Anti-Slavery Society 50th Anniversary Commemoration, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - American Missionary Association, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - American Missionary Association, 1871 (Box 2 (oversize), Folder 57)
  - Battle of the Boyne, 1865–1876 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - The Conditions and Wants of Liberia by Jehu T. Dimey, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Cultivation of Cotton in Africa by Benjamin Coates, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Central African Company "Limited", Circa 1840-1870 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Fliers, Circa 1859-1960 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Freedman's Mission Aid Society, 1870–1894 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - International Migration Society, 1894–1898 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - International Migration Society, 1895–1897 (Box 4 (oversize), Folder 77)
  - Maps, Circa 1850-1877 (Box 4 (oversize), Folder 78)
  - Meeting of Colored Citizens, 1858–1873 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Oxford and Cambridge Mission to Central Africa, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Program for Flower Service, address by William St. Hill Bourne, Circa 1840-1910 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Writings by Esther Bourne
    - "The Snow Storm", 1857 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - "To the Evening Star" (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Writings by George Bourne
    - "Anti-Slavery Lecture 4th of July 1837" by Reverend George Bourne at Newburyport, Massachusetts (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - "Beware of Popery", 1840 (Box 4 (oversize), Folder 79)
    - "Biblical Criticism", Undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - "Biblical Exposition", Undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - "Communion of Christians at the Lord's Table", Undated (Box 4 (oversize), Folder 79)
    - "Irish Superstitions", Undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - "Is Baptism Regeneration?", Undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - "London Eclectic Review", Undated (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - "Origins of the Jesuits", Undated (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - "Shiloh", Undated (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - "Wash Thine Heart From Thy Wickedness", Undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Writings by Theodore Bourne
    - "Biographical Sketch of Reverend George Bourne", Undated (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - "Reverend George Bourne The Pioneer of Anti-Slavery in America", Undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - "Confessions of Thomas Paine or How he Wrote the Age of Reason Made to Reverend George Bourne in New York City in 1805", 1871 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - "The Bell of the Atlantic", Undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - "Children's Hymn", Undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - "Life", Undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - "To Minnie", 1855 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - "Tears of Joy to my Mother", 1845 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - The Vow of Washington (A centennial poem by John G. Whittier) Response of Patriotic Americans, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Clippings, Undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Writings by William Oland Bourne
    - "After Reunion", 1865 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "Before Union", 1854 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "Excelsior", 1875 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "Mother!", Undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "Say Not the Dead are Dead", Undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "Taken Home", Undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - "A Thousand Lustrous Stars Arise", Undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Writings by William Hill St. Bourne
    - Taken Home, Undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Writings by James Montgomery
    Copy of a small portrait of James Montgomery included.
    - "Evening Time", Undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - "Sowing Seed", Undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Writings by Samuel W. Seton
    - "To Montgomery a Xtian Poet", 1826 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Writings by John Greenleaf Whittier
    - "The Centennial Hymn", Undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - "A Centennial Photo", Undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - "The Eternal Goodness", Undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - "The Reformer", Undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Writings by Helen Maria Williams
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Writings by Others
    - "Beautiful Flowers" by Hazel Hawthorne, Undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - "The Withered Flower" by Harold Hawthorne, Undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Unidentified Writings, Circa 1813-1910 (Box 5, Folder 102)
- Personal Papers, Circa 1800-1910; Series III
  Personal Papers includes genealogical records, illustrations, photographs and objects. Two photographs, one of George M. Bourne and one of his driver can be found within the series. Objects include rosary beads, spectacles and spectacle cases.
  - Blank genealogical record book, Undated (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Drawings by Dorothy Pierson, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Ephemera, Circa 1850-1910 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Family tree, wills, marriage certificates, and obituaries, Circa 1800-1919 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Four rosary beads, Undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Hair of George and Mary Bourne, Circa 1793-1851 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - "Maid, Wife, Mother", Undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Photographs of George M. Bourne and driver, Circa 1890-1910 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Envelopes, Circa 1800-1919 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Two pairs of spectacles and two spectacle cases, Undated (Box 6)